Guide to the J. Frank Dobie Papers
The Wittliff Collections
- Works, 1914-1982; 1922-1964; 2982
  - Magazine Articles, 1919-1963, undated; 2988
    - Original drafts of "The Hour of Reading" (1919) and published version in The Texas Review (October 1920), 1919-1920; 3079 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - "Cowboy Songs" and "A Cowboy For to Be, or The Story of the Kansas City Kid," drafts, correspondence, 1924-1929; 3080 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - "The Texas Longhorn's Dying Bellow, Pleas for Preservation of State's Great Symbol," in The Cattleman, 1926 and "The Trailing Longhorns," in Frontier Stories, 1928, 1926, 1928; 3081 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Various drafts of articles, 1931-1932, 1937; 3082 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - "A Corner Forever Texas," pamphlet (undated), "The Jeepy Jackrabbit," in Natural History (January 1943), "Old Bill, Confederate Ally" (1943), untitled galleys (1945), "J. Frank Dobie on Libraries," pamphlet and draft (1950), and "The Brush Country of Texas," in the Lincoln Mercury Times (November-December 1950), 1943,1945,1950; 3083 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Unfinished review of The Eyeturner, undated; 3084 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - "Poetry and Prose at Georgetown" (Winter 1956), "Talking Back to the Censors" (Summer 1962), and "Hunting Cousin Sally" (Summer 1963) in Southwest Review, "The Roadrunner in Fact and Folklore" (May 1, 1956) and "A Close Touch with Wild Turkeys" (November 29, 1956) in the Texas Orinthological Society Newsletter, "Ab Blocker: Trail Boss" in Arizona and the West (1964), "Observations and Reflections of a Deer Hunter" (undated), "For Years We Three Sat Together," in The Texas Observer (July 26, 1963), other drafts (undated), 1956, 1962-1964, undated; 3085 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Lectures and Speeches, 1916, 1927-1964, undated; 2989
    - Lectures, drafts and notes, 1927-1956; 3086 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Notes and drafts of speeches, 1932-1950; 3087 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Notes for speeches on the literature of the range, 1947-1957; 3088 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Notes and research for speeches on writing craftsmanship, 1951-1959; 3089 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Notes and drafts of speeches on the Southwest, 1916, 1931-1934; 3090 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Drafts of speeches on various topics, 1945, 1952-1954, undated; 3091 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Articles from various Colorado newspapers reporting Dobie's speeches made in January 1934 with handwritten outlines of the speeches themselves, drafts and notes regarding other speeches, 1934-1948, undated; 3092 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Quotes, commemorations, 1961-1964; 3093 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Radio and Television, 1932, 1946, 1957, undated; 2990
    - Radio programs, correspondence, and scripts, 1932; 3094 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Radio programs, scripts, drafts, 1946, undated; 3095 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - NBC Television, Wide Wide World presents "Texas, U.S.A.," on February 3, 1957, final draft of the script, January 24, 1957; 3096 (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Personal Papers, 1898-1988, undated; 1913-1964; 3097
  The first subseries within this group of records, Family, contains a family photo album of mostly 19th century photographs of the Dobie and Byler families. Also included are the family bible from which Dobie's father read nightly and two of Dobie's own bibles given to him as gifts: one in 1905 from W. H. Butler and the other from his family in 1908.
  The next set of files, entitled Graduate Education, contains class notes, the Masters thesis, theater programs and newspaper clippings from Dobie's Columbia University days. Despite Dobie's statement in Some Part of Myself that he destroyed a "kind of diary" he kept at the time because he "was so disgusted with the sentimentality in it" (185), there is a diary herein which for the most part describes his reactions to the New York theater.
  In the third subseries, World War I Service, is found Dobie's army uniform, his shipping trunk, and military documents. Dobie enlisted in the Army May 17,1917 but was not shipped to Europe until October of 1918 shortly before the armistice of November 11. He never saw action but was able to use the opportunity to see something of Europe.
  The next subseries, Teaching, contains grade books, teaching notes, lectures and diaries. It includes the notes from the lectures Dobie gave at Cambridge University in 1943.
  Household Records and Personal Effects, the fifth subseries, contains property deeds, income tax records, invoices, mementos, personal items, addresses, wills, and notes. There is information on Dobie's homes, lifestyle and interests. The file named Workfiles and mementos contains miscellaneous envelopes, empty files, clippings and articles including Walter Prescott Webb's "The Search for William E. Hinds."
  The next subseries contains correspondence. The majority of these letters are from Dobie to Bertha detailing his experiences in the army. Other letters to Bertha were written during various separations and discuss family, personal matters and Dobie's writings. They also mention Dobie's work with the Texas Folklore Society and his various research interests. The other major correspondence in this subseries is the letters of Roy Bedichek. Bedichek was director of the University of Texas Interscholastic League by profession but a student of nature by predilection. Bedichek often met with Dobie and historianWalter Prescott Webb for barbecue or at Barton Springs swimming pool in Austin to argue and philosophize. Prodded by Dobie and Webb, Bedichek became a writer of lyrical books on nature at the advanced age of 70. His letters discuss animal stories, politics (especially Texas politics), and mutual friends--University of Texas president Homer Rainey, Folksong collector John Lomax, political commentator John Henry Faulk, Western historian Henry Nash Smith, Walter Prescott Webb and Texas Folklore Society editors Mody Boatright and Wilson Hudson. Also included here are some letters from Isabel Gaddis, a friend who collaborated with Dobie on I'll Tell You A Tale, published in 1960.
  Dobie died on September 18, 1964. The seventh subseries, Dobie's Death, contains the many telegrams and condolence cards sent to his widow along with funeral arrangements, the memorial record book and newspaper clippings about Dobie's accomplishments.
  The eighth subseries, Writings about Dobie, is a collection of clippings, articles and papers on J. Frank Dobie gathered by his wife Bertha and his nephew, Edgar Kincaid. A few of the clippings concern Roy Bedichek or Edgar Kincaid. There also is a file on the Paisano Fellowship, the grant set up as a memorial to Dobie. His beloved ranch west of Austin was deeded to the University of Texas, which, along with the Texas Institute of Letters, manages a fellowship for selected Texas writers and artists. The award enables the writer or artist to spend six months on the ranch with a stipend in order to work on projects free from distraction. The first fellowship was granted in 1967 to Billy Porterfield.
  Photographs, the final subseries contains photographs of Dobie, his wife Bertha, and their family and friends. There are publicity photos, photos taken on Dobie's research trips, and pictures clipped for research. Included are photos of Dobie and Bertha on their ranch or entertaining friends.
  - Family, 1898, 1905, 1908, undated; 3101
    - Family photo album, 1898, undated; 3110 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Dobie family bible, undated; 3111 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Pocket bible, to J. Frank Dobie from W. H. Butler, 1905; 3112 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Bible, inscribed from Dobie's parents, 1908; 3113 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Graduate Education, 1913-1914, undated; 3102
    - Columbia diary, clippings, 1913-1914; 3114 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Term paper for English 244 entitled "Macbeth's Relation to Holinshed", March 15, 1913; 3115 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Notes on English Prose in the 18th century, 1913; 3116 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Essay entitled "The Senses and Description", undated; 3117 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Masters thesis "Thomas Heywood: The Golden Age", 1914; 3118 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - World War I Service, 1914-1921; 3103
    - World War I army papers and personal effects, 1917-1920; 3119 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Contents from Dobie's wallet, 1914-1921; 3120 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Teaching, 1916-1944, undated; 3104
    - Grade books, 1916-1924; 3121 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Grade books, 1924-1930 and 1923-1924 Oklahoma A & M College student directory, 1923-1930; 3122 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Attendance record (1930), grade book (1932), University of Texas directory, 1930, 1932, undated; 3123 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Clipping (1922), High school graduation program listing Dobie as speaker (May 21, 1915), Composition (English I) notes (undated), 1915, 1922, undated; 3124 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Teaching notes, undated; 3125 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Homer Rice Rainey inauguration at the University of Texas, programs (1939) and magazine from the University of Texas Centennial Celebration (1936), 1936, 1939; 3126 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Notes for lectures on American history at Cambridge, 1943-1944; 3127 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Address Book-England, postcards of France, undated; 3128 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Household Records and Personal Effects, 1937-1964, undated; 3105
    - Pocket diaries, 1949-1952; 3129 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Property deeds, 1948-1959; 3130 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Membership certificate from Pedernales Electric Cooperative, mementos, 1948, 1952; 3131 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - House and ranch notes, undated; 3132 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Income Tax Records, 1942; 3133 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Income Tax Records, 1943-1946; 3134 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Income Tax Records, 1947-1950; 3135 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Income Tax Records; check record, 1953-1959, 1963; 3136 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Income Tax Record: Invoices, 1959-1961, 1963; 3137 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Income Tax Records: Invoices, 1960-1963; 3138 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Work files and mementos, article about John C. Duval, undated; 3139 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Personal effects, including white linen Palm Beach suit and silk tie, typewriter, and Dictaphone machine, undated; 3140 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Stationery, undated; 3141 (Box 17, Folder 3-4)
    - Phone list and inventory of books, undated; 3143 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Appraisal of Dobie's Collection of Western American Art, 3144 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Wills and revisions, 1937-1964; 3145 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Articles and speeches about Dobie, 1964, undated; 3146 (Box 17, Folder 8-9)
  - Correspondence, 3106
    - S. D. Harmon (1914) and Genaro del Bosque with translations (1916), 1914, 1916; 3148 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Letters to Bertha from Army, 1917-1918; 3149 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Letters to Bertha from Army, 1918; 3150 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Letters to Bertha from Army and clippings, 1918; 3151 (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - Letters to Bertha from Army, 1918; 3152 (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - Letters to Bertha from Army, 1921, undated; 3153 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Letters to Bertha and clippings, 1927; 3154 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Letters to Bertha and clippings, 1927-1928; 3155 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Letters to Bertha, clippings, and photos, 1929-1930; 3156 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Letters to Bertha, 1931; 3157 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Letters from Roy Bedichek, clippings, 1924-1947; 3158 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Letters from Roy Bedichek, 1947-1951, 1953-1959; 3159 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Bedichek, reviews and scraps, 1947, 1957, undated; 3160 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Isabel Gaddis, 1959; 3161 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - To and from various correspondents, includes photos and belt buckle, 1922-1946; 3162 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - To and from various correspondents, 1950-1964; 3163 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Christmas pamphlets, 1947-1957; 3164 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Dobie's Death, 1964-1988; 3107
    - Sympathy telegrams, 1964; 3165 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Funeral, September 20, 1964; 3166 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Memorial Record Book, 1964; 3167 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - Condolence letters (A-G), 1964; 3168 (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - Condolence letters (H-R), 1964; 3169 (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - Condolence letters (S-Z), 1964; 3170 (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - Condolences, 1964-1965; 3171 (Box 20, Folder 1-4)
    - Articles, clippings in memoriam, 1964-1983; 3175 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Articles, clippings in memoriam, 1964; 3176 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Articles, clippings in memoriam, 1965-1988; 3177 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Writings about Dobie, 1964-1991; 3108
    - Clippings about Dobie, 1964-1975; 3179 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Paisano, 1966-1967; 3180 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Clippings, 1967-1971; 3181 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Address of Ralph W. Yarborough to the Potomac Corral of the Westerners at the Cosmos Club entitled "Frank Dobie: Man and Friend", April 27, 1967; 3182 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Reviews, 1967; 3183 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Application for Official Texas Historical Marker for Dobie's house - made to the Texas Historical Commission State Marker Program, 1990; 3184 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - Henry Louis Alsmeyer, Jr. "J. Frank Dobie's Attitude Towards Physical Nature," dissertation, Texas A & M University, December 1973; 3185 (Box 21, Folder 9-10)
    - Page S. Foshee, "Dobie, Coppini and the Cenotaph," Southwest Texas State University, History 5350, Fall 1991; 3187 (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Photographs, 1906-1964, undated; 3109
    - Miniature photographs of Dobie's parents, Richard Jonathan and Ella Byler Dobie, 3188 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - J. Frank Dobie and Bertha McKee (1908, 1910, 1912, 1914, 1916), program from his high school graduation (1906), 1906-1916; 3189 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - J. Frank Dobie and Bertha McKee, photos and negatives from Mexico, 1924-1925, 1929, undated; 3190 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - J. Frank Dobie and Bertha McKee, Mexico photos, 1937, undated; 3191 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - J. Frank Dobie and Bertha McKee, Mexico photos and negatives, undated; 3192 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - J. Frank Dobie and Bertha McKee, Mexico photos, undated; 3193 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Research, 1937-1964; 3194 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - J. Frank Dobie, Bertha, and friends, 1929-1964, undated; 3195 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - J. Frank Dobie, Bertha, and friends, 1953-1961; 3196 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Paisano, undated; 3197 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Bertha after Dobie's death, undated; 3198 (Box 23, Folder 4)
- Bertha McKee Dobie and Edgar Kincaid Papers, 1926-1974, undated; 3098
  This series contains family letters to Bertha. The bulk of the correspondence is from her mother and mentions Dobie, his work, and his trips to Mexico. The letters also discuss Bertha's family, health and gardening. Included too are Bertha's gardening columns, and various sundry clippings, pamphlets and articles that she collected about Dobie and other matters of interest to her. Edgar Kincaid's family records and photographs of Kincaid at a book signing for The Bird Life of Texas are also present.
  - Family letters, 1926-1927; 3199 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Family letters, 1928; 3200 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Family letters, 1927-1928; 3201 (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Family letters, 1929; 3202 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Family letters, 1930-1931; 3203 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1961-1970; 3204 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Bertha Dobie's gardening columns, 1933, 1935, undated; 3205 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Bertha Dobie's gardening columns, undated; 3206 (Box 24, Folder 5-6)
  - "Yardman by the Day," draft, undated; 3208 (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Bertha Dobie's information file, clippings, notes, sketches, newsletters, 1937-1972; 3209 (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - Pamphlets, artwork, 1964-1966, undated; 3210 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Webb Memorial, LBJ Library, 1970-1972; 3211 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, includes Bertha Dobie's obituary, 1961-1974, undated; 3212 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Southwestern Reviews, 1942-1967; 3213 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Edgar Kincaid family records, includes a chapter of The Bird Watcher's America entitled "Golden-Cheeks of the Edward's Plateau" by Edgar Bryan Kincaid, Jr. (1965) and an inventory of books donated to Texas A & M University Libraries, undated, 1965, undated; 3214 (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Photographs of Edgar Kincaid book signing, undated; 3215 (Box 25, Folder 6)
- Artifacts, undated; 3099
  This series contains personal items that belonged to J. Frank Dobie, including clothing, toiletries, a ceramic roadrunner figurine, pipes, a typewriter, and a Dictaphone machine.
  - Ceramic roadrunner, pipes, leather razor strop, belt, undated; 3216 (Box 26)
  - J. Frank Dobie's handmade shoes, undated; 3217 (Box 27)
- Newspaper Clippings, undated; 3100
  This series is housed in one oversized box and contains unprocessed original newspaper clippings collected by J. Frank Dobie.
  - Unprocessed original newspaper clippings, undated; 3218 (Box 28)